Presenter: So now we’re going to talk to Martha,
who works in the Human Resources department of a large publishing company…
Martha: Hello.
Presenter: Martha,
do you think this idea of one hour of work and 20 minutes of rest would work in a big company?
I mean, if you think about it, in an eight-hour day, and taking lunch into account,
people would actually only be working for about six hours.
Do you think that’s feasible?
Martha: Well, first I’d say that in fact,
in an office environment, that is what actually happens a lot of the time.
I mean, people aren’t tied to their desks for eight hours a day,
they spend a lot of time having conversations with colleagues.
I’m not sure that the office environment really allows you to concentrate for a full hour
without interruption, unless people are really disciplined.
But, as a concept, I think it’s probably a good idea, and might make people more productive.
Where I’m not sure that it works like that is for people who are working from home,
because they may not want to take those 20-minute breaks;
they may prefer to work non-stop for a few very intensive hours, much fewer than eight,
and then stop altogether.
And they can do this because they have fewer distractions
– they can switch off emails and Skype and things.
But, actually, they might have achieved the same in three or four intensive hours
as someone in an office does in an eight-hour day.
Presenter: What about the four-day week, something that has also been suggested?
Can’t this sometimes cause a problem for employers and, indeed, employees?
Martha: Both of the large organizations I’ve worked for have been supportive of flexible working,
and quite a few people do work a four-day week now.
The issue is that some people who do this – who work, say, 32 hours a week very productively,
instead of the full 40 – they do get paid less.
But they think that they achieve as much as someone doing five days’ work
because they work more efficiently, and it’s not fair that they only get paid for four days.
On the other hand, so the argument goes, they do get the flexibility to have a longer weekend,
which may suit their lifestyle better.
But of course, it does depend on the job; obviously,
if an employer needs staff to be in the office every day for some reason,
then that’s going to be less feasible.
I know for employees nearing retirement age, at my company,
we’re very open to considering that option for them if that’s what they want,
and I do think that this four-day-week pattern is going to become more common in the future.
Presenter: Do you think either of these ideas would work for students,
i.e. that they should take a 15-minute break for every hour of work,
or only work four days a week?
Martha: Well, most university students could easily work that way
if they wanted to and maybe it would be more productive.
But somehow, in practice,
a lot of students I know seem to do very little academic work for a period of time;
they leave things till the last minute and then suddenly work all night
when they’ve got an exam coming up!
I’m pretty sure that that’s not the best way or the most productive way to work, though.